Guide to the Ipas Records, 1965-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ipas records 1965-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ipas.
186 linear feet Extent: 139,500 items
Ipas works around the world to increase women's ability to exercise their sexual and reproductive rights, especially the right to safe abortion. The collection documents this global nongovernmental organization dedicated to ending preventable deaths and disabilities from unsafe abortion.
ipas
Language: Material in English Spanish
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection restricted until 2025 with the exception of the Publications series. Researchers must receive prior authorization from Ipas in order to access the material in these series.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Ipas Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2011.
Historical Note
Founded in 1973, Ipas is a nonprofit organization that works around the world to increase women's ability to exercise their sexual and reproductive rights, especially the right to safe abortion. Through local, national, and global partnerships, Ipas seeks to end preventable deaths and disabilities from unsafe abortion and to expand women's access to safe, respectful, and comprehensive abortion care, including contraception and related reproductive health information and care. Ipas strives to foster a legal, policy and social environment supportive of women's rights to make their own sexual and reproductive health decisions freely and safely.
Ipas' executive directors and presidents/CEOs since 1973 have been: Elton Kessel 1973-1974, Jorgen Jenk 1974-1976, John Tomaro 1976-1979, Charanne Clarke 1979-1982, Edward Meldahl 1982-1985, Katie Early (McLaurin) 1985-1991, Forrest C. Greenslade 1991-1999, Elizabeth S. Maguire 1999-
More information about the organization and its activities can be found on its website: www.ipas.org.
Collection Overview
Collection documents this global nongovernmental organization dedicated to ending preventable deaths and disabilities from unsafe abortion. It consists of Ipas publications from 1975 through 2011, including both electronic and printed formats, as well as Latin America and Caribbean Programs material from 1987-2006, Africa Programs material from 1973-2004, Asia Programs from 1985-2006, Marketing/Technology and Logistics/Product Promotion, and Distribution material from 1973-2003, Chronological Files from 1974-2004, Program Files and Internal Documentation from 1970-2006, Executive and Management files from 1965-2006, Training and Service Delivery Improvement from 1988-2006, and Policy Unit files from 1996-2006.
Acquired jointly as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture and the Human Rights Archive (Duke University).
This collection guide is being regularly updated as materials are added to the archive. Please contact Research Services if you would like to use this collection.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Ipas; Abortion; Human reproductive technology; Human rights; Reproductive health; Right to health care; Women's rights; Women -- health and hygiene; Women's health services -- Africa; Women's health services -- Asia; Women's health services -- Caribbean Area; Women's health services -- Latin America; Women's health services -- United States; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Publications, 1975-2011, (26 boxes)
  This series contains Ipas and non-Ipas publications and audio/visual materials. For a complete list of the Ipas publications in this series, please contact Research Services staff. Electronic publications have been removed from the collection and transferred to Duke's Electronic Records server. Please contact Research Services staff if you are interested in using this material.
  - 1975-1997, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1998, (5 folders)
  - 1999, (5 folders)
  - 2000, (2 of 3 folders)
  - 2000, (folder 3 of 3) (Box 2)
  - 2001, (6 folders)
  - 2002, (8 folders)
  - 2003, (4 of 12 folders)
  - Multimedia materials: Advocating for Safe Abortion in Africa (Box 3)
  - 2003, (folders 5 through 12)
  - 2004, (4 of 6 folders)
  - 2004, (folders 5 to 6) (Box 4)
  - 2005, (8 folders)
  - 2006, (6 of 9 folders)
  - 2006, (folders 7 to 9) (Box 5)
  - 2007, (4 folders)
  - 2008, (5 folders)
  - 2009, (4 folders)
  - 2010, (1 of 5 folders)
  - 2010, (folders 2 to 5) (Box 6)
  - Film reels, (7)
  - Non-Ipas publications (Box 30-31)
  - Publications with significant contributions from Ipas (Box 32-33)
  - Non-Ipas audio-visual materials (Box 65-66)
  - Non-Ipas publications (Box 67-68)
  - Ipas audio-visual materials (Box 74)
  - Video tapes from "Expanding Access: The Role of Mid-Level Providers in Menstrual Regulation and Elective Abortion Care", Dec 2-5, 2001; miscellaneous video tapes (Box 75-76)
  - undated publications (Box 77)
  - Ipas publications, 1988-2003 (Box 78)
  - Ipas publications, 2004-2011 (Box 79)
  - Ipas publications, binders, and videotapes (Box 80-83)
  - Ipas publications missing from previous shipments: 1992-2011 (Box 109)
  - Non-Ipas publications (Box 119)
  - 3 oversized Ipas publications (Box 128)
- Latin American and Caribbean Programs, 1987-2006, (27 boxes)
  Ipas's first Latin America/Caribbean (LAC) programs began in Mexico in 1983 with demonstration training projects in MVA technique for treating abortion complications. Extensive programs, primarily in training for women's reproductive health service delivery and health systems research, were conducted starting in the late 1980s. The primary LAC program countries from 1987 - 2003 were Mexico, Nicaragua, Brazil and Bolivia (all of which had in-country Ipas offices over this time period), with smaller projects at various times in Peru, Paraguay, Colombia and Chile. Ipas has sold MVA instruments throughout the entire continent. By the mid-1990s, Ipas stepped up efforts in policy and marketing in the LAC region, as overall organizational capacity was enhanced in these areas.
  Areas of highest impact and results in the LAC region by Ipas include: assisting governments in national scale-up of post abortion care initiatives to improve quality of and access to treatment of abortion complications, contributing to reductions in maternal mortality; research cost studies on services; quality of care and instructional tools for improving post abortion care services and preventing repeat abortion via post abortion family planning; establishing legal abortion services where laws have allowed; provision of post abortion care services by mid-level and primary care providers; reproductive health services for adolescents; publicizing the issue of sexual violence against women; and advancement of women's sexual and reproductive rights as part of human rights.
  Ipas's LAC programs were under the direction of various staff during this time period - most notably Harrison McKay (Director of Programs in the late 1980s), Joan Healy (Director of Programs in the 1990s), and Virginia Chambers, Ipas's first LAC Desk Director (regional director) beginning in 1998.
  Series restricted until 2025. Researchers must receive prior authorization from Ipas in order to access the material in these series.
  - Mexico: donor proposals and reports; Frente/Campana project; IMSS sol files; ILE files; Monterey Symposium files; country annual report; adolescents; nursing schools; monthly reports; pro-choice alliance files; small grants program; video proposal; country workplan; SE project; Alianza; sexual violence, 2001-2003 (Box 7)
  - Mexico: photos of trainings; Access project files; mid-level project files; ILE project files; IMSS Sol; Mexico office trip reports; monthly reports; Mexico country plan; Mexico program summaries; job descriptions and benefits; training numbers, 2000 (Box 8)
  - Mexico: Legal Abortion project files; IMSS files; mid-level rural project files; Mexico office communications; trip reports; AAA-World Bank project files; Access (marketing) project files, 1999 (Box 9-10)
  - Mexico: marketing files; IMSS-Sol project files; modules project files; SSA project files; Morelos project files; Safe Motherhood; Mexico office communications; training numbers, trip reports; radio spots; Dr. Ortiz, 1998 (Box 11)
  - Mexico: correspondence; 2nd USAID PAC meeting files; IMSS Solidaridad project files; marketing files; Morelos files; sustaining file; INOPAL files; 1997 (Box 12)
  - Mexico: IMSS project files; SSA project files; Merelos project files; USAID PAC meeting project files; Mexico office communications; Mexico sustaining program file; APHA abstract; PAC strategy meeting, 1996 (Box 13)
  - Mexico: training notebook; Mihoacan/Zacatecas; Sinora/Sinaloa program files; INPER; Geo Gonzales; Safe Motherhood; IMSS; Pathfinder project; Oaxaca; proposals/reports; legal docs; MVA licensing, 1987-1995 (Box 14)
  - Peru: communications with practitioners; correspondence; proposals; reports, 1988-1997 (Box 15)
  - Brazil, Peru, Paraguay, Columbia, Chile: working files; Facultad de Obstetricia project files; midwifery schools; proposals; ICM presentations; PAC/PAFP meeting; marketing; reports, correspondence; fundraising; MVA in medical schools; proposals; country plan; workplan; Ayacucho project; project development; Flora Tristan; dissemination workshop; collaboration; correspondence; management cycle; working files; Araucania project files, 1993-2002 (Box 16)
  - LAC miscellaneous countries without programs (Box 17)
  - LAC regional management and planning working files; LAC partner organizations, 1989-2003 (Box 18)
  - LAC Regional Projects, 1995-2003 (Box 19)
  - Non-Ipas publications (Box 20-22)
  - Bolivia: working files, 1993-1995 (Box 23)
  - Bolivia: working files; ODA files; INOPAL file, 1996-1998 (Box 24)
  - Bolivia: DFID working files; DFID final report; training numbers; country plan; correspondence; proposals; trip reports; logframe; reach numbers, 1999-2000 (Box 25)
  - Bolivia: team meetings; correspondence; monthly reports; evaluations; marketing; DFID working files; Frontiers working files; reach numbers; violence symposium; program review; fundraising; USAID PAC evaluation; development consultant; medical/nursing schools; site coordinators; reach numbers; management cycle, 2001-2003 (Box 26)
  - Brazil: trip reports; project development; donor documents; contracts; reports; correspondence; Jabaquara; CRSMNADI; CEPIA; Adesse; da Mota; MEAC; Pathfinder; Cesar Cals; Chizuro; UFRJ Maternidade; SOS Corp; ECOS; Jabaquara working files; legal abortion program; BART files; communications; donor report; MVA cost/benefit report, 1989-1996 (Box 27)
  - Brazil: working files from all years (proposals, reports, database, conferences, equipment; activity reports, correspondence, etc.), 1997-2001 (Box 28)
  - NICA: Si Mujer; Tipitapa, DeProsse eval; Jarquin; hospital reports; MINSA; Work Bank evaluation; working files; correspondence; country plan; country team; general file, 1985-2002 (Box 29)
  - LAC: Mexico 82-06: PAC 06; OB/GYN congress 06; Alliance report 05-06; program planning 04; Gire 03; program binder 02; MVA sales/OBgyn congress 97; MVA training 97; workshops 97-04; IMSS Solidaridad 97 working files; donor reports 02-06; donor reports/proposals 97-98; proposals/reports 97; donor comms 97; consultants 97; marketing project 97; comms 97; Morelos midwives training 97; Safe Motherhood mtg 97; product registration 97; monthly updates 97-97; research projects 96-97; Oaxaca PAC training/eval 96; office ops 96; Andrea Saldana reports 96; marketing projects 95-97; Mexico office registration 95; natl pop plan 95; MVA studies 95-95; Zacatecas PAC study results 92; Sonoroa/Sinaloa working files 89-92; MCH training 88; Monterrey clinic 82; El Oro project 86-87 (Box 124)
  - LAC region: Bolivia/Brazil/Monitoring: Bolivia 00-06: Bolivia office 05-06; MOH Norms; donor reports/proposals 06; consultant reports/sexual violence 03-04; partner agreements 02; donor reports/proposals 02-04; program binder 02; eval of hospital services 00; PAC 95-06; Coms 92-05; PAC study 01:Brazil 00-06: sexual violence; comms; legal reform 06; donor reports/proposals 06; lit review 05; AMPARO 04; Follow-up on complications 04; reports/studies 02-03; program binder 02; donor reports 01-06; operations 01-02; strategic plan 00-04; marketing 00-05; LAC region Monitoring notebook: 04-05 (Box 125)
  - LAC Region: Venezuela: 86-87 Uruguay: PAC training report 05; reform 03-04: Peru: legal 04-05; training course 01-02; training numbers 02; program binder 02; study tour comms 01-02; reports 01-02; Ayacucho PAC 01; reports/conferences/mtgs 00-01; eval Condo Grande project 02; donor proposals 01; program planning 01; development 01-01; country plan 00-01; country team marketing 00; partners/agreements/mtgs 00-01; corresp 00; office ops 00-03: Paraguay: background; Nicaragua: program binder 02; donor reports/proposals 01-06; corres MMB; La Campana 28 de September 04-07; ICCO project eval 06; ICCO contract 02; Rosa case 03; proposals 03; fundraising 01; ops 01-03; Ob/Gyn mtg report 01; Honduras: MVA training 88; El Salvador: MM study 06; Guyana: background 01-02; corresp 99-03; media clippings 99-01; Ecuador: coms/trip report 02-04; MOH agreement 02; donor report hospital training program 86-89; working file hospital training program 86-89; Colombia: legal reform women's Link contract 06; AVSC project 96-97 (Box 126)
  - LAC region: Internal training 06; EC 06; small grants 06; strat planning 06; donor reports/proposals 05-06; med abortion 05; SV report 05; donor reports/proposals 03; key partners FLASOG/FIGO 05; GTN 04; org planning 04; WHO strategic committee 05; SV comms 03-04; SV 02-04; SV background; country summaries 03; M&E 02; newsletter 02; development comms 02-04; program review 02; UNFPA SV donor; reports/proposals 01-04; advocacy comms 01-04; MVA training sales 01-04; donor reports/proposals 01-02; impt comms 01-03; MVA training numbers 01; regional management 01; program activities reports 00-01; strat plans 00-04; regional update 00; presentations 99-02; regional summary 99-04; strat planning 99; strat planning 98-04; conferences 97-04; marketing 96-97; trip reports 96-06; LAC PAC (LART) 95-99; conferences 86-87 (Box 127)
- Marketing/T&L/PPD Unit, 1973-2004, (9 boxes)
  Ipas was founded in 1973 to complete development of the Manual Vacuum Aspirator (MVA) technology and to undertake its distribution worldwide with the overarching goal of ending women's preventable deaths and disabilities from unsafe abortion. Ipas focused its MVA marketing and distribution efforts on the product's attributes as a safe, low cost medical instrument appropriate for all types of health care facilities, especially low-resource and outpatient settings where trained mid- and lower-level clinical providers (in addition to physicians) could provide these critical services for women.
  Ipas dedicated staff to its MVA marketing efforts starting in the early 1990s. Starting in 1997, major grants allowed the organization to greatly expand marketing efforts by hiring marketing professionals, undertaking country-based marketing activities to improve local access and supply, positioning MVA as a safe and appropriate alternative to other post-abortion and abortion methodologies, forming private and public partnerships for product distribution, performing more sophisticated market segmentation analyses, expanding the product line, and increasing training options and tools. Sales and distribution of MVA increased dramatically accordingly, resulting in more women being served worldwide. Ipas also re-designed the MVA aspirator to make it more durable, easier to use and maintain, and lower in cost; the new MVA was launched in 2004.
  Ipas's marketing efforts were under the direction of various staff during this time period. Katie Early (McLaurin) headed up marketing activities in the 1980s, and Jennifer Potts was International Marketing Associate in the 1990s. Starting in 1997, Kim Beer was the first Director of Marketing and Gil Barner joined in 2000 as Vice President of Reproductive Health Technologies. The unit was renamed Technology and Logistics (T&L), followed by Product, Promotion and Distribution (PPD) between 2000 and 2004. Darryl Rubenchik became Vice President of PPD in 2002, followed by Nadine Burton in 2003 and Jay Drosin in 2004.
  - Marketing/T&L/PPD 1975-2001: Internal files; external documents; manufacturer and distributor information and agreements (Box 34)
  - Marketing/T&L/PPD 1996-2001: Donor proposals and correspondence; partner organizations (Box 35)
  - Marketing/T&L/PPD 1988-2003: Marketing strategy binder 97-98; Manual/binder for MVA training projects 1994; clinical and programmatic literature on MVA 2003; Marketing R&D files (MVA re-design and launch, Denniston dilators, emergency kit; rigid cannulae tests) (Box 36)
  - Marketing/T&L/PPD 1997-2001: Country files (alphabetical) (Box 37-40)
  - Marketing/T&L/PPD 2000-2006: J Potts marketing 94-96, management 97-00, E/C Europe marketing plan 00, East Africa marketing plan 00-05, distribution 01-02, UNC School of Public Health project 02, internal newsletters 02-03, internal presentation 05, Europe MAP 05, sales reports 05, MVA Access Plan 05, PPD Educ and promotional materials 05, US program marketing 05, ME/Europe marketing plan 06, pricing study 06-07, distributor survey analysis 06, MAP interim donor report 06, product dossiers 06, donation analysis 06, Albania 05, Denmark 05, Bulgaria 06, Egypt 06, Georgia 05, Iran 06, Kuwait 06, Russia 04, Syria 06, Turkey 06, UAE 06, UK 07 (Box 105)
  - Marketing/T&L/PPD: MVA Redesign and Launch 01-05: Redesign chrono 01-02, branding 02, chrono 02-03, chrono 01-03, chrono 04-05, Global Launch mtg 05 (Box 106)
- Africa Programs, 1973-2004, (18 boxes)
  Ipas's first Africa programs involved establishment of clinics for treatment of women's complications resulting from incomplete abortion and provision of contraceptives in Ghana in 1981. In 1983, Ipas sponsored demonstration training projects in Nigeria in MVA technique for treating complications resulting from incomplete abortion. Hospital-based MVA training projects followed in Nigeria, Zaire, Zambia, Kenya in the late 1980s, and research projects commenced in the early 1990s in Zimbabwe and Kenya. Starting in the mid-1990s, Ipas programs in Africa expanded dramatically, due to donor grants dedicated to organizational efforts in east and southern Africa, along with growth in overall organizational capacity in policy/advocacy and marketing. In 2000, Ipas established the Africa Alliance for Reproductive Health and Rights to coordinate and support country- and region-wide activities and extend programming to countries where Ipas did not have a country office. By 2000, Ipas had in-country offices in Nigeria, Ethiopia, Uganda, Ghana and South Africa, and a regional office in Kenya for the Ipas Africa Alliance. Ipas sold MVA instruments throughout the entire continent during this time period.
  Areas of highest impact and results in the Africa region by Ipas include: assisting governments in national scale-up of postabortion care initiatives to improve quality of and access to treatment of abortion complications; conducting health systems and cost research studies on services; developing quality of care and instructional tools for improving postabortion care services and preventing repeat abortion via postabortion family planning; establishing comprehensive abortion care services in countries where laws were supportive; creating national standards and guidelines for best practices in comprehensive abortion care; advocating for reform to expand legal indications for abortion services; documenting coverage and utilization models in safe abortion care; provision of postabortion care services by mid-level and primary care providers; provision of reproductive health services for special needs populations, such as refugees, adolescents and people with HIV/AIDS; and advancement of women's sexual and reproductive rights as part of human rights.
  Ipas's Africa programs were under the direction of various staff during this time period - most notably Harrison McKay (Director of Programs in the late 1980s), Joan Healy (Director of Programs in the 1990s), Jennifer Potts (Africa Desk Director, or regional director) and Khama Rogo (Vice President for Africa and VP for Medical Affairs) in the late 1990s, Eunice Brookman-Amissah (Vice President for Africa and Director of Ipas Africa Alliance) starting in 2000, and Uche Ekenna as Africa Desk Director starting in 2003.
  - Nigeria Programs 1984-1991: FEMOPE marketing 85-96; Dr. Bamgbose 86-88; Lagos project correspondence 86-92; Zaria correspondence 87-88; programs overview 87-91; correspondence 87-98; Tubi reports 88; Port Harcourt 88-91; background 88-96; equipment 90-93; Zaria 89; market research 89-90; Tubi correspondence 89-90; research 89-91; Zaria 90-91; Lagos reports 90-95; HAAL 90-97; Tubi correspondence 91-92; Nigeria IV project working files 91-92; Prof Ojo correspondence 91-94; Zaria 91-94; FMOH/PAFA 91-95; PATH collaboration 91-95 (Box 41)
  - Nigeria Programs 1992-1995: misc correspondence 92-93; Ayo Tubi reports 92-95; Lagos project correspondence 92-95; donor proposals/reports/correspondence 92-96; Ayo Tubo correspondence 92-95; private MD trainings 92-96; Nigeria V working files 93-94; Expanding Access project working files 93-96; ADB project 94; Zaria reports/proposals 94-96; Dr. Shittu 94-96; reports 94-97; Laniyan consultant 95; IFH report to ODA 95; LSS curriculum 95; Lagos correspondence 95-96; NYSC training 95-96; NARD training 95-96; NMA 95-96; Ayo Tubi correspondence 95-96; Tubi reports 95-96; MOH project 95-96; NGO collaboration 96-97; CHAN working files 95-97 (Box 42)
  - Nigeria Programs 1996-1999: country summaries 96-99; trip reports 96-97; CHAN project working files 96-99; REACH tracking 97-98; SMT background 97; field reports 97; strat planning workshop 97; articles 97-99; donor proposals/report 97-99; SMT 97-00; PACNET meetings 97-01; SMT meetings 97-01; strategic plan 98; papers 98; background 98-99; SMT mailings 98-99; field reports 98-99; comms 98-03; chief 99; AGHA 99; Ayo Tubo correspondence 99; planning 99; policy 99 (Box 43)
  - Nigeria Programs 2000-2003: reports 00; meetings 00; plan/proposal/strategy 00; history 00; SOGON 00; PAC to scale workshop 00; correspondence 00; NGO constitution 00 ;women's health organization 00; LRRDC 00; EMPARC 00; IFH 00; SMT correspondence 00-01; Tubi correspondence 00-01; PRIME 00-01; Pathfinder 00-01; IFH 00-01; correspondence 00-03; donor proposals/reports/correspondence 00-04; small grants 01; SOGON/NMA/WONCA 01; ARFH 01; CAUP 01; NAMMN 01; trip reports 01; INTRAH 01; planning 02; MVA plus launch 02-04; research projects 03; registration and lease 03 proposal/correspondence 98; donor reports 98; DFID Year one working files 99; country summary 99; marketing 99; DFID year 2 00; contracts 00; reports 00-01; team meetings 00; DFID year 3 01; Goldman Judin 01-02; proposals 01-02 (Box 44)